hello I'm your host David Barnard and my
guest today is Steve p young founder and
CEO of app Masters the app marketing
agency that helps grow apps faster
better and cheaper on the podcast I talk
with Steve about black hat app
optimization the benefits and drawbacks
of hard paywalls and why despite apple
and Google's best efforts so many apps
still use dark patterns it even
blatantly break the rules
Steve thanks so much for joining me on
the podcast today it's been a while I've
been meaning to have you on and finally
getting to do it today I feel excited
David finally got the invite I've been
waiting for the invite
well I've been thinking through what
would I really want to talk to Steve
about I mean you cover so many things
we've had people on talking about ASL
you talk a lot about ASL we'll probably
talk some ASO today you share all sorts
of tips for optimization but what I
really want to talk about what finally
got me like okay I gotta have Steve on
is App Store ethics so you and I have
been talking for years and we probably
first met 12 years ago early on one of
the things we talked about very
specifically was that I was super Indie
developer I'm not going to be aggressive
with my paywall which I've totally come
first circle on that not even being a
good way to describe it we can get into
that but I had this super pure Indie
mindset of build a product and they will
come and I'm going to follow every Rule
and be like this upstanding citizen and
you're a little bit more like this is a
business morality is a spectrum I'm not
gonna break the law I'm going to be
careful not to break Apple's rules but
I'm gonna run a business and do what it
takes to succeed and so that was the
start of our conversations and years ago
and the reason we had that conversation
is that I was getting to a point where I
was fed up because I saw all these other
developers bending the rules breaking
the rules using dark patterns and here I
am struggling with my business feeling
like I need to not be aggressive with my
paywall and it's not that I wanted to do
anything against the rules or anything
like that but I was just even realizing
hey I need to think about this more as
not this passion project this is feeding
my family and so that's how it kicked
off was like I was like hey let's talk
real stuff but what I was seeing in the
App Store was that so many apps were
breaking the rules and so many apps were
using dark patterns so many apps you're
bringing a knife to a gunfight if you
were trying to compete in any category
and then when you do market research I
mean I was talking to people who it's
like hey look I see see four wallpaper
apps making millions of dollars that
must be like a really great opportunity
I'm going to build a wallpaper app and
I'm like look go download those four
wallpaper apps and figure out why are
they making a million dollars they're
using all sorts of dark patterns they're
using 15 a week subscriptions and things
like that so let's start breaking it
down you know I've even talked recently
that there are still tons of apps
breaking the rules so like if you're an
app developer in the App Store trying to
succeed with your subscription app and
you're looking at competitors you're
looking at the landscape I think it's
important to understand all the
different ways that people are breaking
the rules and even using dark patterns
and even just being smart about their
business that you may not have thought
of so that's all a spectrum right from
clearly breaking the rules clearly
immoral to like hey this is just smart
business and not even questionable at
all I've been talking for a very long
time but I think it was important to
kind of set up this conversation for
actually really calling out the dark
patterns the breaking of the rules and
then we're not gonna philosophically
dive into what's moral and what's not
moral and how you should run your own
business but we're just gonna talk about
what people are actually doing on the
App Store so let's kick it off what is
the worst thing that apps are still
doing to this day that people should
understand that their competition might
be doing I think maybe we'll start off
with reviews because that's the one
thing I do not do anymore we used to in
2015 because we I remember our
conversations and I'll be like I would
always live off in the gray that's where
I like to live but don't buy reviews
2015 I figured out that if you have
keywords in your app store reviews that
would actually help your keyword
rankings and we would see apps go up in
the keyword ranking just by one or two
reviews with the right keywords in there
and I stopped doing that and stop buying
those reviews and so the way way I feel
about these black hat strategies is you
got to do what you got to do to get you
to a certain point and then after you
get that certain point I don't believe
these are long-term strategies but I
think the zero to one is just the
hardest phase of any journey and so I'm
gonna do whatever it takes to get to
that one and then once it's there yo I'm
good let me figure out everything else
and I hear a lot of big companies doing
these reviews they're just putting a ton
of paid reviews and Apple's gotten
better at this apple is friendly Google
will suspend you but that's one thing
that people say hey Steve you have a
good review source and I go nope I don't
do that anymore don't do it you're gonna
get in trouble do not touch that part
yeah but what you're saying there is you
don't do it anymore but tons of apps
still do it I would assume it's just
been a big cat and mouse game for the
last decade or more now in 15 years for
15 years now Apple's played a cat and
mouse game of all these different dark
patterns but from what you've seen seen
people are still buying fake reviews and
fake ratings right and they're just
finding more sophisticated ways to avoid
Apple's detection yeah I mean I can see
it right now because I have a source and
I'm on the website right now and I can
see multiple apps that are on this
website asking for reviews so yes yeah
and again I mean the whole point of
having this conversation is when you're
running your app
and you're doing market research and
you're trying to understand why is this
other app being more successful why is
this other app ranking highly for a
keyword when you're doing your app store
optimization one thing you got to keep
in mind is that people are probably
breaking the rules and this is one big
way to do it right yeah reviews and then
we can get into some of this other stuff
too David is keyword campaigns keyword
install campaigns those I feel like I
know a lot of big companies I had a
conversation one-on-one with the big
company specifically talking about this
and how to best leverage it and all that
stuff and I knew they were already
running it and so with the review side I
was talking to a big client of ours and
I was like hey we can do this review
stuff if you need help like we already
got it taken care of oh I didn't know
these big companies were doing that
right and that's why I was starting to
talk about it more because I was like yo
that's not fair you guys got this
massive budget and you're doing this
stuff that's not fair to us Indies so
that's why I like to bring it up and
talk about these issues and I don't try
to shy away from them because I just
feel like yeah they already have an
advantage Over Us in these so how do we
gain that Advantage let's step back what
is a keyword install campaign why would
people do it what is it buying ratings
and reviews are are pretty self-evident
but I think this one and again this goes
to probably 80 percent of our listeners
on this show will not know what this is
and yet their competitors probably do it
so what is a keyword boost campaign so
it's essentially you get a bunch of
people to search for a keyword and
download your app and hacking the
algorithm to make the relevancy of this
keyword closer to your app right so
there's a bunch of different sources out
there if you just Google it around but
it is that you pick a keyword and then
you boost that keyword by getting
downloads from that keyword so
essentially like an ASA campaign if
you're really aggressive with an ASA
campaign put on exact match and just put
a high cost per tap and you're just
trying to get tap tap tap tap tap on
there I don't think that has the same
benefit but essentially that you're
getting people to search for a keyword
to download your app and hacking the
algorithm to get you higher in the
keyword rankings from what I understand
Apple has tamped that down a little bit
where like it doesn't always work
anymore but it does still work
apparently it does still work and so the
key is to find a keyword that is pretty
low competition from an ASO standpoint
that has a lease a search score of 30
and we did this for an app and
essentially we ran a keyword boost
campaign within the initial launch phase
we got it to number one it's stuck it's
still number one for this keyword and
there were two keywords think with a
space and without a space right one word
versus two word and then we both had
decent traffic we got it to be number
one for both terms and now it's getting
downloads for free organically so that's
what I mean David Wright like we're not
utilizing this strategy anymore we found
this keyword I don't think keyword
optimization is enough anymore you need
to give it a little bit of boost but if
you find the right keyword that has low
competition then no one's paying
attention to then using these sort of
black hat Strat energies you can get it
to number one and once you're number one
like you're golden don't worry about it
anymore you don't have to do anything
and that app is just getting it from
zero to one and now it's making money
it's making five thousand dollars a
month just organically pretty much and
so we got it to a certain point and then
we just stopped yeah you're still doing
this do you worry about Apple Banning
one of your accounts I'm not worried
David and here's why because I can run
this for any app I can run it for your
app you want to know I did it I can run
it for my neighbors app I can run it for
any app in the app store it does not
matter we've heard black hat strategies
where people will leave once our reviews
for some of their competitors now I
don't do that type of stuff I'm here to
win my own game and I don't like to
penalize and so when I'm running the
other stuff sometimes I'm doing keyword
research is this a valuable keyword and
so I can run this for any app for
anybody I'm not hurting them I'm only
helping them but it's my way of getting
a sense of is this keyword can it move
if I gave it a little bit of a juice
right and then that way I can do some
market research around that and so then
the problem is and I remember this from
poof decade ago maybe more yeah was that
there were some big apps that were
accused of doing Shady stuff and their
defense was we didn't actually do it a
competitor did it to try and get us
kicked out of the store
and there's almost no way I can think of
any way for Apple to figure out I mean
aside from hiring private investigator
and I don't know how crazy Apple gets
and trying to figure this kind of stuff
out but how would you know if Steve did
it for me without me knowing or a
competitor did it to try and get me
kicked out and then this gets to the
Crux of app review being a really hard
thing there's been a lot of press the
last few years about especially from
Costa talking about all the scam apps on
the store and then just the reality of
it is there's so many things that Apple
just can't enforce well and as much as
they have gotten better at detecting
various things it's this cat Mouse game
where if you just do it different and
then they can't detect it again
personally I think I draw my moral line
maybe a lot differently than you do and
that's where I think our listeners are
all going to be on a spectrum right of
like how far you decide to go like I
personally would not not feel
comfortable writing a keyword-based
campaign I mean this is why we're having
like this conversation though is that to
me that feels like cheating but your
point is valid that if so many other
apps are cheating if you're not cheating
you're not playing the same game that
everyone else is playing like how do you
succeed in a marketplace where
I I don't know what percentage it is but
it's probably a small percentage but
it's a small percentage of the more
successful apps are cheating I'm doing
quality fingers if you're not watching
the video again I consider it cheating
but it's part of the game that's being
played on this Marketplace and if you're
not doing it you are at a disadvantage
so if like me you don't feel comfortable
doing it you at least still need to be
aware that it's happening so that you
can plan your strategies around
understanding that the competitors might
be doing these things absolutely yeah
David I'm not here promoting to do these
strategies from a legal perspective I'm
not promoting any of this stuff all
right you run your own risk don't listen
to me and take my advice on any of this
stuff it's just that's my goal is look
there are people doing it that are
humongous companies and your goal
whether you want to do it or not is up
to you but it does work this is how you
do it it is entirely up to you and I've
talk to so many developers David that I
think the apps business in its most
simplistic form and feel free to
disagree on this is just a funnel how
are you going to get downloads whether
it is because I've talked to people
who've done it on tick tock on Twitter
on Reddit on Facebook organically ASO it
doesn't matter you have to think what is
the top of the funnel and then you have
to think okay once I get the download
how am I get them to convert and so all
these strategies we're talking about you
don't have to do any of this stuff it's
just you have to think about the funnel
because I'll talk to people I don't even
care about ASO I've got Twitter ads
running profitably right or I've got
Facebook ads running profitably so
there's many ways to cut and win at this
game I just want to make sure people are
aware of what's happening in the space
yeah what are some of your other top
um edgy edgy things yeah yeah that's a
good way to put it
all right so I'll rattle through a few
one of the things we used to do was you
know the top three reviews show up
because they're the most helpful yeah
you can 3D touch that and you can sort
of hack which reviews show up first so
you can get a lot of your friends to
vote the five star that has the most
famous now you can try having the right
keywords in there to try to show up
higher the first three so you just get a
bunch of people to 3D touch that and
then hit helpful and then that hacks the
algorithm that way and just to be clear
well and 3D touch isn't really a thing
anymore but so we call that long press
long press is Apple's terminology so
what Steve is saying is you go to the
App Store you find a review that you
like that is promoting your app
mentioning the keywords that people care
about demonstrating the intent that it's
what's going to get you a conversion in
the app and you long press on that
review and it's kind of a hidden feature
which this is one of those things it's a
hidden feature and so it's probably
gamed as much as it's actually used by
like real people because who randomly on
the App Store is long pressing a review
and then when you long press it brings
up a little dialogue of did you find
this helpful and then you mark it as
helpful and that actually influences
which ones show up at the top but how
many real people are actually doing this
versus how many of your competitors are
leveraging this to get the best possible
reviews to show up first in the Sorting
so that's what you're talking about and
then do you have anything else to add
there no I mean that front on the review
side I'll leave with that the other edgy
thing would be during the paywall view
waiting five seconds to show your ex so
that's another edgy thing that people do
where you just have the little X just
show up a little bit five seconds a
little bit later and then that way it
does increase Revenue it does work but
it's up to you on whether you want to do
it yeah and so then the edgy part of
that is that you're kind of forcing
people to think that it's a hard pay
wall even though it's not I mean and so
this is one of those where like maybe
five years ago I would have been like oh
yeah that's definitely something I would
never do that's so deceptive this is the
next phase maybe we should get on to is
is that there's a lot of these kind of
hacks where and this is a perfect
example where is it immoral to not show
the close button so that people who
otherwise wouldn't have started a free
trial now start a free trial because I
think that's the only way forward
yeah for some people that's probably
going to be a little edgy but on the
flip side one of the things I've been
thinking a ton about with freemium these
days is that people understand that
things cost money and showing them a
paywall is a reminder of that and if
somebody is getting a ton of value out
of your app is it really that much of a
detriment to show the paywall on launch
again five years ago I'd have been like
showing the paywall on every launch
that's like a total dark pattern and
then I see my fitness pal doing it and
my fitness pal is a great example
because I've used that app off and on I
subscribed for a year track my calories
really closely lost some weight then I
stopped using it then I subscribed for a
couple of months I mean just last week I
was using it to check in on how I'm
doing calorie wise and I launched the
app I get a paywall and for me I hit the
little x button and they don't delay the
X at least in the paywalls I saw I
wouldn't be surprised if they do at some
point or do it other paywalls or
something but I hit the X and I kind of
feel like hey I'm cheating the system
I'm I'm getting value out of this app
and I'm not having to pay the advanced
features are super valuable and so I
have paid off and on to get those more
valuable features but I've been thinking
about that how the user psychology of
seeing paywalls frequently is not even
necessarily always a negative thing so
for some people yeah it's annoying like
ah why are they showing the paywall like
I'm just trying to log my calories but
then it's oh yeah I'm logging my
calories and using this app completely
for free but there's actually a paid
version and personally now when I'm
seeing paywalls that's my psychology is
hey hahaha hit that X and I'm getting it
for free so any thoughts on that and any
other thoughts kind of along those lines
I know we talked about personally hard
pay walls and I was sharing some data
with our app now David I was against a
hard paywall when we launched this so I
want you to understand the full story
we're talking my co-founder he's a
developer we purchased this app he was
like hey it's about to go it has no X
and I didn't know what a hard paywall
was at the time I was like why that
seems hella me dude why are we doing
that and he's like well that's how we
built it and for me I like to think of
myself as just somebody like that's a
growth hacker so I'm like look I'm not
going to fix that let's let the data
kind of figure out what's going to
happen and so we launched it as is even
though I was opposed to it but then I
looked at the data and I was like whoa
that's a crazy we went from one to two
thousand to ten thousand just like that
with Organic downloads I was like wow
that's crazy and so when we had to put
the X in there we dropped five thousand
now our app is super basic well you said
you had to put the X Apple made you yes
Apple's coming around and here's how I
feel about this and I'm happy to say
this publicly obviously but like it
depends on your reviewer some things are
against their T's and C's some things
are just who you get to actually
physically review your app and so while
they might say that this is against our
rules like unless I see it on paper I
see so many apps doing it that I'm like
you can't say this is against your rules
if I see these many apps doing it right
part of my job is looking at a ton of
that perhaps and I see so many and I get
to distill a lot of this but we had to
put the X and our revenues dropped from
ten thousand to five thousand now the
reason why I feel like a hard paywall
works for us is because it's such a
basic app there's not that many features
involved in it it's a one feature type
of app that like once you're in you're
kind of like that's it or maybe you
wouldn't purchase and maybe we haven't
done the math on LTV and all the
retention since we're forcing it but
when I looked at the numbers the numbers
speak for itself so I'm not going to be
religious about the fact that this is
immoral I'm gonna figure out hey the
numbers are telling me this is a good
app people are staying on people are not
asking for refunds so people are getting
good use of it that's the whole reason
we bought the app it's to your point
earlier David and I think I'm glad you
said it too because I feel like hey you
spent so much time so many resources so
much money on developing this app if I
can get away with using your app for
free guess what I'm gonna do use it for
free right like but you spent so much
time if your goal is to just make the
world better and have me use your app
for free good on you mate
congratulations but if your goal is to
build a business then you have to start
thinking about how can I be more quote
unquote aggressive with my marketing
because if you feel like you go to great
app if you feel like you're actually
helping people then why aren't you
charging we're doing this stuff for free
but in the end you're gonna have to pay
us if you want to work with us you're
going to have to pay us if you want to
work with Revenue cap eventually you're
going to have to pay and so we built a
great service that we believe in and our
if our service isn't good it will fail
it will crash and you can look at the
numbers it's not like we're not giving
away a trial we're doing a hard paywall
and if the trial percentage was very low
then you know we had a bad product but
our trial to paid is on average it's 35
percent let the numbers tell me what to
do it's funny you brought up uh hard
paywall I wanted to get to that because
I'm actually doing a hard paywall in my
weather app that's gonna weather up 3.0
is launching in the next probably before
this podcast airs but the reason I'm
doing a hard pay while I really struggle
with this for all the reasons you're
talking about I mean everything from I
don't want to be that app I don't want
to look scammy I don't whatever but
here's the thing is that with this
update I'm releasing so much of the
value is in widgets and complications so
we built a really cool widget for the
app and we built a really cool Apple
watch complication well guess what
that is really expensive for a weather
app and so I could not come up with a
good way to give that away in any kind
of freemium scenario you can't put an ad
in a widget that's a terrible experience
I think Apple even has rules against
putting ads and widgets can't put an ad
in a complication the actual value prop
of the app cannot be given away for free
and the app itself is good but we've
been more focused on the widgets and
complications lately and so we don't
want to give away the app for free as
part of a freemium and show ads and then
the ads is a whole nother thing and like
I've been begging and you and I were at
a conference last September and on stage
I was saying we need for the
subscription app industry so this is my
pitch again the subscription app
industry needs a good ad platform that
does higher quality ads because I had
Google AdSense in my app and I kept
getting bad reviews I kept getting
support requests of why are you showing
gambling in your app they weren't
actually game gambling but it was the
slots games where it would be a really
annoying animation and so people are
going into my app I do genuinely care
about the experience people have in my
app and the experience was crappy no
matter how many buttons I pressed in
there people were getting ads for guns
people were getting these Casino looking
ads people were getting all these ads
that they found offensive and that were
annoying and a detraction from my
product and so even if I could which
with a weather app because every time
you open the app it costs me money even
if I could only give away the app itself
and not the complications and widgets I
don't have a way to monetize that I mean
actually the app is losing money right
now because we pulled the ads out in
anticipation of this revamp and doing
the hard paywall and so I've been losing
money for like a year on that app
because it's got no ads in it and it's
got a lot of free users and it doesn't
have many subscribers so anyways I'm
going on and on about my own personal
strategy but because I think there's
valid reasons to do a hard paywall and I
wrestled with it but we're doing a hard
paywall and this is a case where and I
think Apple does allow hard pay walls
but I think you might have to convince
them and I think I have a pretty strong
argument here of why I need to do a hard
paywall on this app so our hard paywalls
a dark pattern well honestly I'm doing
it because I want to create a better
experience in my app if you start the
free trial you're going to get
everything
and I'm gonna lose money on every free
trial yeah for people who don't convert
because I'm probably gonna lose
10 cents to 20 cents maybe even up to 50
cents or a dollar on every single free
trial I offer depending on how heavy a
usage the average free trellis uses
so I'm actually giving value away for
free in that seven for day free trial so
doing a hard paywall as much as I would
have been against it three or four years
ago as much as some people might still
think it's a dark pattern I pretty much
have to do it with this app to deliver
the experience I want to deliver so yeah
that's where I landed on it and honestly
from a business standpoint and having
talked to you I'm probably going to make
more money by doing a hard paywall than
if I did do freemium for this app and
there's something I want to experiment
with in the future if I can figure out a
way to do some kind of monetization with
a better ad Network or something to have
some freemium experience but it's tough
it's tough to make that freemium work
when you have those kind of costs yeah
completely agree like I said I was
against it too I was looking at other
like AI tools right that help you create
content and stuff it is all a hard
paywall like don't get religious about
this stuff like you go to any of your
favorite web tools literally a hard
paywall I'm looking at Jasper AI right
like I was like all right what's a
Content tool that I love that's an AI
tool yeah here here's what we do but
it's a hard big wall and AI is a great
example right I mean some of the AI apps
aren't offering free trials because it
costs them a lot of money I'm
complaining about weather app costs but
like these AI apps often have very high
costs and so even a free trial could
lose their money so yeah that's a great
example to bring up is that AI
specifically I think we may even see a
bigger wave of hard paywalls shorter
free trials and things like that is it a
dark pattern well when you're paying so
much for the these AI training and AI
inference and running the AI models it's
not you're giving away value if you
can't give it away for free you need to
paint wallet yeah agreed any other dark
patterns to wrap up this segment
um let me well here I'll bring one up
and and see what you think and see if
you have experience with this I was
looking at a few apps recently where
they're pushing folks to the web I think
I actually got to it through a web ad so
it's not that they're necessarily
pushing people to the web but it's like
a web ad and so I'm in safari
and the typical like long onboarding
thing and then I get to the paywall and
it's like start your one week free trial
it costs us ten dollars to give you a
trial which
probably BS I'm going to calculate it
and maybe I'll do something like this in
my app where I'll tell people in the app
that hey it cost me a dollar to give you
this free trial because it is costing
something now ten dollars to give people
a seven day free trial I don't know what
app is actually how they're doing the
math on that
um but then it gets options do you want
to pay the full 8.75 that it costs us to
get and it's like really specific as if
they like really ran the numbers do you
want to pay for the full cost of the
trial or do you want to pay two dollars
or you want to pay one I was like okay
I'll pay a dollar seven days dollar
whatever
Apple pay comes up I confirm it now they
have my credit card info on stripe so
then I keep going through all the
onboarding and at this point I'm just
like yeah it's so much tax I'm just
scanning I'm not reading everything at
some point I hit a button that was like
start your actual subscription now I
actually I'll take it back
I think it was fairly clear but I was
expecting to tap that button and then
the Apple pay sheet come up and then I
cancel the Apple pay sheet but I tap the
button and then they just immediately
charge the card like 70 bucks because
they got the credit card info with the
one dollar free trial which again I feel
like that was a little bit of a dark
pattern telling me it cost 8.75 cents
for my free trial or whatever but then
they have the credit card on file so
then any continue button any label
that's not necessarily explaining it
again I think the app that I was using
actually did have the price and it did
say something I don't want to totally
throw any app doing this under the bus
but they could technically because this
is a web Apple's not reviewing it they
could technically just have a continue
button that doesn't say anywhere on
there and they could charge directly to
your credit card after that so have you
seen this and what do you think of this
as a pattern I mean not as much but as
much as I like to talk about this black
cat stuff I'm not a fan of all that
stuff because sometimes I'll see this on
upside all pages you add to cart you
want to add this like oh my God you're
really trying to sell like that stuff
but fine I go no as long as it makes it
clear that I can say no but I'm trying
to look for the no I mean I know because
I come from the web side of things right
and so I know this stuff works I'm not a
big fan of those either yeah I want to
bring value and not try to scam you and
I feel like once you're getting to the
scammy again I was against a hard
paywall and so once you get into the
scammy's phase I feel like oh yeah let's
not go there but one thing I would say
for the hard paywall stuff if you've got
sort of a meditation app if you got
really good content in the app consider
maybe my friend of mine tested a hard
pay wall versus a lot of lock content he
has a crossword app and he just made one
free puzzle and he tested those two
variations because I was first I was
like dude you're giving away too much
you're giving way too much away for free
because in the end humans were against
friction if you make it frictionless for
us cool we'll just stay there we're
never gonna pay you but if you built a
good app that people highly engage by
the way app so you tested that and he
saw a boost in revenues by doing a hard
paywall and then he tested hard pay wall
versus just more lock content and so
what I've been saying look if you don't
want to do the hard pay well just lock
up a lot of your content if you look at
the big apps now like calm you can see
that a lot of their meditations are all
locked up and so what that gives you is
the user can see a variety of content
that you have but obviously they'll have
to pay to access any of the content yeah
that's a great counterbalance because we
were talking about the benefits of a
hard payroll but it's not going to work
for every app eventually I'd like to
figure out a way to do freemium in my
app because there is a there's an aspect
to people who've gotten more and more
more comfortable I think in apps
starting a free trial and realizing like
hey I can use this totally for free get
as much value as I can for seven days
and then it's so easy to cancel and I'm
a big fan of Apple and Google payments
because they make it so easy to cancel
on the web it's I mean like this
specific app I had to do a chargeback to
get my money back the one that I was
talking about where I accidentally
clicked which that's a whole other topic
if you're doing web stuff you don't have
apple enforcing rules on this kind of
potentially more scammy stuff but what
you do have is people who feel scammed
are going to leave bad reviews and are
going to do chargebacks with their
credit card which gets expensive and
gets you booted from stripe if you go to
scammy you'll find out pretty soon when
stripe boots you from their platform
again it's a similar thing people
complain about app review and there's
legitimate complaints I'm still have
lots of complaints that I send to Apple
about app review but hey this exists
throughout the whole world right you're
running a restaurant you're going to
have the health inspector come check
things out out you know you're running a
scammy web app you're going to have
stripe shut you down people talk about
oh free market and Apple's very
restrictive and I've got my issues with
that but like don't pretend you can just
do whatever you want anywhere you want
every business has rules that they have
to follow in different countries they
have to abide by the laws of those
countries and different platforms that
they're working with have to abide by
those rules and so it is what it is so
that was a deep rabbit hole but you were
talking about hard paywalls and how
that's not always the optimal strategy
so I think you're absolutely right it's
like there are times when having one or
two things unlocked and then having
everything else locked is a good
experience because people actually get
to see the value it's essentially all
these little mini paywalls you see the
little lock button and it's like oh I
want that but I know I have to pay for
that don't let my hard paywall talk bias
you to think that that's the way to do
it freemium is a great strategy for most
apps and again I think what I was
talking about I think the future of
subscription apps is better freemium is
finding ways to monetize those users who
aren't going to monetize via
subscription because like in reality
socioeconomically and just mentality
wise there's just tons of people who are
never going to pay for your app and so
the best thing we can do as an industry
is be able to give more value to those
who just aren't going to pay and find
ways to monetize and then yeah lock
features lock premium content lock what
makes sense and every app needs to
explore what actually makes sense to
lock versus free and part payroll is
kind of a cop-out just lock everything
but in some ways a good starting point
and then now potentially I get to work
backwards of like okay now how can I
give away something for free but yeah I
think freemium is the right path forward
for most apps but it's just a struggle
to make it work well any tips on getting
that balance right other than locking
content because content's an easier one
where I think you can give away a couple
of meditations you can give away a
couple of this or a couple of that but
in more productivity apps that gets a
little tougher I would say lock up as
much as you can I think a lot of times
people here we can go off this tangent
when people are developing like a to-do
list app it's like oh I'll ask for a
review after 10. I'm like how many of
your users get to 10 really low percent
so maybe you should ask for a review
right after the first one and then get
them or during the onboarding process
which we've seen work really well too to
balance off buying for reviews will show
the review prompt during the onboarding
process or show it right after a paywall
even if they can X Out hit them with the
review prompt and so what I would say is
I think too many times I look at
developers I'm like you've just giving
away too much for free you spent all
this time you're so proud of this app
but yet you're so afraid of charging for
it look I've been there I feel the same
way I'm trying to increase our prices
and I'm like I don't want to do that yet
I still want to be really affordable to
the Indies and be the most effective and
affordable app market agency so I feel
the same struggle as much as I'm seeing
here increase your prices or be more
aggressive paywall I still feel it when
it's our baby it still feels a little
bit different to do it when it's our
baby so I still feel it but that's why
you need other people to talk to you
they can be like look this is a great
app like I'll talk to somebody like yo
this is a great app how many downloads
you get what how much are you making I'm
like you know David we worked on this
Android because people are like Steve
this wouldn't work on Android and I was
like challenge accepted and so I was
like all right I threw an offer out to
the audience like look I'm willing to
work with anybody I'll give you a
discount on some of our packages but
here's what I want the case study and so
one of our clients Steve this is for an
absolute prank type of app he's like
look at the charts a lot of the stuff
that we're talking about a lot of things
I've been sharing from a monetization
perspective I feel David it's just more
psychology based more than hey is this
the right moral based stuff so when you
have a paywall show it during the
onboarding we've talked about Anya she
said that was the biggest tip that I
would have done once she did that her
Revenue stubble and she has a panic
she's is rooted panic attack so she's
like I'm not going to do a hard paywall
because if you have a panic attack you
want to feel relief you don't want to
absolutely pay so like cool so she
allows people to x out but when she
added it it doubled their revenues right
this is against it and I was like what
there's no way a friend of mine told me
this tip in like end of 2017 18 range
and I was like there's no way that works
he's like nope double my revenues I just
let the data and I think too many times
we as experts you and I as experts we
tend to say what is our opinion and so I
always want to differentiate when I'm
saying like here's my opinion ask David
too or ask other people that might have
the same thing or this is data driven
and so I try to show data when I'm like
look I feel confident that this works
and a lot of times people ask me are you
sure and I'm like look I wait I don't
just share everything I wait dude I wait
till like two or three and I'm like okay
I feel pretty confident sharing this
because the last thing I want to do is
share something I feel worked once and
it doesn't always work because the
people like oh that didn't work and
whatever you're sharing whatever how
much data you have there are things that
will and won't work yeah exact specific
apps so at the end of the day and this
is one thing I've struggled with over
the years has an indie developer with
limited resources limited development
time is that I have not done a lot of
testing in my apps and it's been to my
detriment is that we launched something
and it's clearly not working but it's
hard to unwind what you did wrong and
then try something new and try something
new and try something new somebody was
asking me recently I go what's the
biggest mistake actually it was in the
sub Club Community a little pitch for
the community here if you're uh
listening to podcasts and haven't heard
of the community yet we have a private
Community I think Steve's in there if
you're not I need to get you in there I
think you're in there but anyways
there's an open question in the
community it'll be a little old by the
time this podcast here is but it's like
what's the biggest mistake and so people
are sharing their mistakes and so I was
typing mine up and I think the biggest
mistake I've made is not learning from
mistakes is like you launch and you need
to then try and find a way and it
doesn't have to be a b testing it
doesn't have to be super sophisticated
it can just be hey this launch trial
starts went way down okay let's try
something new I had a big release with
my lunch and a Pro app a few years back
to capitalize on the home screen
customization made like 20K that month
but then we didn't iterate to maintain
that lead and so to this day there's
tons of home screen customization and
widget apps that are making tons of
money and I totally missed the boat on
that because we had this big launch and
then we didn't learn from the launch of
what was working what wasn't and then
keep building the features that we're
going to keep people around and there
were obvious things but this is what's
hard if you're in India out there you
don't have a ton of resources but that's
how you actually grow instead of running
the app into the ground like I have with
some of my apps is that when Steve says
hey do a hard paywall you do a hard
paywall but then you look at the numbers
if it's not working for your app don't
do it do something different and don't
take any of the advice we share on this
podcast receive shares if he's sharing
it if I'm sharing it it's probably that
we've seen it work but it's not going to
work for every out of money so yeah hey
David I'll say this the biggest mistake
I made if I were starting the app
business today I would say I don't care
what I think my opinion does not matter
we're gonna let the data speak for
itself whether it's ASO whether it's
hard paywall whether it's trial
conversion whatever long pay well
whatever it is let the data play out
because a lot of times how we're
building new apps these days is we're
letting the keywords because I'm going
to be more Reliant I don't want to pay
for traffic right so I'm going to be
reliant on more keyword organic
downloads but I'm letting the keywords
tell me which app to build and I want to
stay in a field where I know people are
willing to convert there's a painkiller
versus vitamin so I'm going to build an
app that is more of a painkiller versus
a vitamin and from all the categories of
apps that we work with the mental health
space the fitness health and fitness
space tends to have the highest
conversion rates so how I'm building my
apps moving forward is looking at the
categories where I know there's High
conversion rates and look looking at the
keywords and really figuring out all
right what are some keywords that a lot
of people are not paying attention to so
my opinion does not matter everything is
based on data yeah Thomas uh Petty I
don't know if you listen to the last
podcast up there's two episodes ago now
but he was sharing on ad creatives he's
like look I've been doing this for 12 15
years now he said on the podcast like I
am no better than throwing a dart at
pictures on the wall in deciding which
ad is going to be the most performant I
mean when you think about it that really
applies to like your paywall design your
paywall call to action whether or not
you do a hard paywall or not you and I
have a ton of experience have talked to
so many developers have worked on so
many different apps but even then you
don't know what the right strategy is
until you try a few things and again
bigger apps yeah you can do super
sophisticated a b testing smaller apps
just try it yeah the numbers should be
big enough to see the difference and
this is where people get really hung up
on statistical significance and
everything like that but at the end of
the day if you don't see a dramatic
change then pick what you think is a
better experience but you'll make some
changes where it's just obviously better
stick with those right and then just
keep trying and yeah if you can and have
the resources do more sophisticated
testing but even then I think there's a
lot of noise in the kind of a b testing
Community when you're a b testing
everything and every little thing and
how one thing affects the other is
really hard to suss out and the whole a
B test everything is tough to execute in
a way that you're actually building a
great product you have to have a really
good team to not just optimize your way
into a crappy app that exploits every
possible like base psychology of
humanity so even if you don't have the
resources you can experiment just do it
and don't be like me launching an app
making some good money and then just not
following through yeah yeah and just
start with the lowest hanging fruit I've
got to many apps where I'm looking at
their numbers and like I think your
screenshots are ugly I think your icon
is ugly what I look at your numbers you
get great organic downloads 25 trial
activation sixty percent child to paid
there's nothing here why would I tell
you to change your screenshots maybe
that might impact it but you're doing
pretty well six figures a month over six
figures a month and so I'm like maybe
play around with the trial variation
it's really about looking at the numbers
and figuring out what the data is
telling you where you should go and what
you should optimize and I think for
Indie developers I'm just going to throw
out a number out of the year but if
you're not making at least a thousand
dollars a month try a hard paywall
because it will force users and it'll
tell you if users actually want or need
your app and if you're hard pay well
your trial activation is solid but you
trial the paid then you need to fix
what's going on in the app right maybe
you need to get them to use it or maybe
they're telling you this isn't a
painkiller this is a nice to have so I
prefer to just be on the free plan and
that way you can really figure out what
to do next and that's why now I've
become a proponent of the hard payroll
especially for the beginning developers
just to get your users to tell you do I
really want your app or not because I
invested it downloaded it and went
through your onboarding but now I'm here
and that's one of the things about a
heart paywall that I think some people
will see as a dark pattern is that yeah
oh well people are going to start their
free trial and just forget but these
days people don't forget I mean yeah
it's like a small percentage we shared
numbers Revenue cat numbers and I've
seen this in our data that there are
apps that have five percent free trial
conversion rates so 95 of people and
some of these are even absolute
three-day free trials so yes people will
forget but it's probably in the low
single digit percentages so if you think
oh well I'm just preying on people
forgetting to cancel maybe but you're
not going to build a business around
people forgetting there are apps that
still do that if you dump a ton into
paid acquisition if if the numbers are
big enough that single digit low
percentage of people who forget to
unsubscribe will drive significant
Revenue but for the average average
developer it's a huge signal are people
converting on the free trial or not and
like you said that's a great way you
switch to a hard paywall and you will
see do people care or do they not care
if it's single digit percentage you know
you're not product Market fit that's a
people forgetting if it's 10 20 people
are finding value out of this so yeah I
think that's a great hack to just as an
early stage figure it out are people
actually finding value all right well
I've talked way too much but as we wrap
up any last minute low hanging fruits I
mean optimize your paywall man that's it
optimize that's the one thing I would do
add it to the onboarding process
optimize your pay wall and then look at
your main page if you do have a freemium
thing and look at your main page I put a
video up how a simple icon change that's
a 57 increase in paywall views there are
two areas that I would just fully
optimize it's your onboarding experience
and it's your paywall whether it's the
plans that you have or whether it's a
long pay wall short paywall whatever it
is those that the two areas that I would
play around with the most and then get
to a stable part for me this is just my
Approach get to a stable part where I'm
driving revenues and then think about
how I can drive more revenues off the
top of the funnel and start operating
this is awesome David thank you yeah
really great advice so are you accepting
new clients yeah if you want to learn
more about us just check out our YouTube
channel I mean that's what I would
suggest I prefer you guys look at the
freemium models back to the freemium
look at our free YouTube stuff go
through that YouTube channel youtube.com
appmasters and if you are interested in
with us it is at masters.com but we got
team of 11 now I have to give a little
pitch because you do you give so much
away for free like you exemplify the
freemium model but if you want to really
get into the weeds with Steve it's going
to cost you money just like if you want
to use my weather app it's going to cost
you money
but the fun thing is this was not just
an ad for your services I've listened to
too many podcasts where it just ends up
sounding like an ad so I appreciate that
you will share so freely if not just hey
come work with me and I'll share the
real stuff you share the real stuff all
the time today on the pi podcast and
then on your YouTube channel so yeah
even if you don't want to work with
Steve he's got some really great content
around all this stuff and you're I
believe in 10 minutes you're gonna go
live on YouTube so I think every Friday
you do live shows oh one minute all
right thanks Steve you're amazing thanks
David bye see you then
[Music]
thanks so much for listening
if you have a minute please leave a
review in your favorite podcast player
you can also stop by
chat.subclub.com to join our private
community
[Music]